Contact

venkatesh.x.ramaswamy@gmail .com

www.linkedin.com/in/venramx (LinkedIn)

Top Skills

Credit Cards
Offshore Outsourcing
ISO8583

Venkatesh Ramaswamy

VP of Engineering at ShareChat San Jose

Summary

Technologist at heart with a strong focus on a results-oriented approach, and a people person. I believe in taking care of people, and the projects follow. Many years of experience dealing with large off-shore teams, completely at ease with upper and executive management, experience with mission-critical and time-sensitive projects impacting real-time payments.

- *Mission statements*:
- o Move things at light speed in organizations when things sometimes move at a snail's pace.
- o Working with totally abstract ideas and shaping them into reality.
- o Crisp, clear and candid communication at all times.
- o Fail, but fail fast. Never hesitate to accept failures and learn.
- o Understand people and their behaviors.

Specialties: Enterprise Software, Cloud Computing, Off-shore development, 4+1 architecture views, Domain Object Models (DOMs), Multi-threaded/processing architectures, Language-agnostic software design, Process and Enterprise monitoring, ISO 8583, external vendor integrations, Real-time payments (ACH, Credit Card, Debit Card) processing and settlements, FP&A and payments reconciliation, Merchant Risk architecture, Customer resolutions/ Dispute arbitration, Large data/volume integrations via ETL

Experience

ShareChat
VP of Engineering
April 2019 - Present (1 year 5 months)
Bengaluru, India; San Francisco, USA

People, Engineering and everything in between.

eBay

Director Of Engineering March 2018 - April 2019 (1 year 2 months)

San Jose, CA

eBay Marketplaces

6 years

Senior Engineering Manager

February 2015 - February 2018 (3 years 1 month)

San Francisco Bay Area

Focusing on People, Code and Process. (in that order).

Agility of a startup in an enterprise company.

Engineering Manager 2

March 2012 - March 2015 (3 years 1 month)

- Back end integration services for 1 year.
- Back end integration and payment services for 1 year.
- Back end integration, payments and loyalty related services for 1 year.

eBay

Quality Engineering Manager

February 2011 - February 2012 (1 year 1 month)

-All front-end and back-end integration services.

PayPal

4 years 4 months

Staff Software Engineer

March 2009 - February 2011 (2 years)

- o Architect-ed, designed, co-developed, delivered and supported a Merchant Risk platform that saved PayPal ~3 bps loss savings over the year (~\$20M at that time).
- o From a design concept to production in rapid time, leading a brand new team in Scottsdale, AZ which also included a new vendor integration.
- o Worked extensively with the ETL team to define the business logic for extractions and transformations.
- o Lead and designed an API integration project with eBay to allow the access of the Resolutions platform via SOA.
- o This supported eBay's launch of the Resolutions platform in US and UK.
- o Lead a team of 9 developers to launch eBay's EU Resolutions initiative via another set of tightly-coupled SOA services and APIs.

Sr. Software Engineer

November 2006 - March 2009 (2 years 5 months)

- o San Jose lead for a team of developers working in Chennai.
- o Expert-level understanding of Debit Card processing, transaction model and reconciliation.
- o Master-level understanding of ACH and Credit Card processing.
- o Enhanced the framework to allow for processing via the STAR network.
- o Designed, presented and developed generic framework for vendor file processing to make vendor integration seamless.
- o Responsible for day to day working and maintenance of various external facing services with First Data, STAR and other networks.
- o Focussed on educating, mentoring, working alongside and growing my Chennai support folks.

Epic Systems Corp.

Team Leader, R&D

June 2003 - October 2006 (3 years 5 months)

- o One of the youngest managers in the company after just 2 years and one of the most technology-oriented group in the company.
- o Joined the specialized projects team to work on innovative and quick time-tomarket products.
- o Creator of an innovate set of programming interfaces that was used by multiple teams throughout the company and thoroughly appreciated.
- o This soon lead to the formulation of a full-fledged team, for which I was appointed the manager in about 6 months.
- o Lead numerous projects through complete life cycles, planning, QA test case validations, handling customer escalations, budget planning, contractual negotiations with third parties, interactions with legal, etc.
- o Presented for two consecutive years at the yearly User Group Meeting in front of 300+ invitees from all over the country.
- o Mentored, reviewed and provided constructive feedback to my direct reports.
- o Traveled to numerous client sites that included some of the biggest HMOs and Hospitals to meet with the executive staff there.
- o Kept it "human".

Education

Indiana University Bloomington

M.S., Computer Science · (2001 - 2003)

Vivekanand Education Society's Institute Of Technology Bachelors, Computer Science · (1997 - 2001)